Marjorie Morse Crunden Papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Marjorie Morse Crunden Papers
1924-1942
Ms Coll 53
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
Marjorie Morse Crunden, the daughter of a Baptist medical missionary in China, was educated in the United States, including at Yale School of Nursing. Correspondence includes letters from her parents; from her fiancé, Allan B. Crunden, a Yale medical student who transferred to Temple University School of Medicine; and from other friends and family. The collection also includes a five-year diary.
Crunden, Marjorie Morse, 1913-2000
Biographical / Historical
Marjorie Morse was born in China in 1913 to Dr. William Reginald Morse and Anne (Anna) Crosse Kinney Morse of Canada who were Baptist medical missionaries in China from 1909 to 1937. Dr. Morse grew up in a large family in Lawrencetown, Annapolis County, Nova Scotia. Marjorie, an only child, came with her parents to the United States in 1924 and remained there for her education after her parents returned to China. She lived with relatives and friends as she attended Newton High School in Newton, Massachusetts (graduated 1930), and Wellesley College (1930-1934), where she majored in sociology. In 1934, she began a three-year program for an R.N. and masters degree in nursing at the Yale School of Nursing. In New Haven in 1934, she met Allan B. Crunden, Jr. of Montclair, New Jersey, a graduate of Georgetown University, and a member of the Yale School of Medicine class of 1937. By the end of the year, she had agreed to marry him after completing her training. Crunden decided at this time that he did not like the "Yale System" with its lack of examinations, and thought that hospital training would be better in a larger city. He returned to Montclair, where he lived with his recently widowed father, and took laboratory and social science courses at Columbia University in the spring of 1936. In the fall of 1936, he resumed his medical education, taking his clinical years at Temple University School of Medicine, Philadelphia. Marjorie Morse continued her nursing education, much of it in hospital wards, in New Haven, West Haven, and on rotations to Rhode Island until her graduation in 1937. Much had to be decided on where and when they could be married and who would marry them. She was a Baptist and he a devout Catholic, she was not an American citizen, and she hoped her paents could attend. In the end, they married in July 1937 in London in a Church of England ceremony. Her parents were able to meet them in London on their way home from China to retirement in Lawrencetown. The Crundens lived in Philadelphia in the school year 1937-1938 where she served as a nurse-administrator at Temple and he completed his medical degree. The following two years, while Allan Crunden was serving hospital residency appointments in Jersey City and New York, Marjorie Crunden obtained an M.A. in education from Columbia University Teacher's College. She served briefly as an assistant in nursing education at Columbia. In 1940 they spent a year in Chicago with Allan Crunden's father. Allan Crunden was called into medical service in the Air Force in World War II. After the war, they lived in Montclair and other locations in New Jersey. He practiced as an obstetrician, while she was active in numerous civic and charitable organizations including the Montclair Board of Education, the Essex County Board of Health, the Montclair Public Health Nursing Service, and the Community Child Study Group of Montclair, which she organized. She was an expert tennis player and a local champion. The Crundens had two children, Robert Morse Crunden, later a prominent professor of American Studies at University of Texas, Austin, and Joan Crunden Lewis.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains sparse correspondence from Marjorie Morse's parents to her; letters from Marjorie Crunden to her mother in 1940-1941; hundreds of letters written every few days from her fiancé and then husband, Allan B. Crunden, Jr., at periods when they were living apart between 1935 and 1940; letters by Marjorie Morse sent as part of a round robin to friends who graduated from Wellesley; and many letters from friends and family. Also in the collection are Marjorie Morse's five-year diary (1932-1936), memorabilia from Newton High School, Wellesley College, and Yale School of Nursing, and miscellanea. There is some material on Morse's training as a nurse, and considerable material, including texts of examinations, on Crunden's clinical training at Temple University School of Medicine. Above all, the letters are a record of an upper middle class courtship in the 1930s. The collection includes a few photos of Marjorie Morse and Allan Crunden and of their son, Robert Morse Crunden, as a baby.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was part of a larger collection purchased in 2015 jointly with the Divinity School Library. The medical missionary papers of Marjorie Morse Crunden's parents are in the Divinity School Library.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: 1. Correspondence. 2. Diary, memorabilia, and miscellany.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Related Materials
Morse family papers: William Reginald and Anne Crosse Kinney Morse, 1909-1941, Special Collections, Divinity School Library, Yale University.
Courtship -- United States; Interns (Medicine); Medical education -- United States; Missionaries, Medical -- China; Nursing -- Study and teaching -- United States; Obstetrics -- Study and teaching; Residents (Medicine); Tennis; Correspondence; Diaries; Greeting cards; Photographs; Medical students; Nursing students; Nurses; Physicians; Crunden, Allan B., 1878-; Crunden, Allan Bernard, 1912-1977; Crunden, Robert Morse, 1940-; Morse, William R. (William Reginald), 1874-1939; Morse, Anne Crosse, 1875-1951; Columbia University. Teachers College; New Haven Hospital (New Haven, Conn.); Newton High School (Newton, Mass.); Temple University. School of Medicine; Vassar College. Institute of Euthenics; Wellesley College; Yale University. School of Medicine; Yale Universty. School of Nursing
- Correspondence, 1925-1942; Series I
  - Letters to and from parents (William Reginald Morse and Anne Crosse Morse), 1925-1942; 1
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries contains letters and greting cards sent by Marjorie Morse's parents in China to her in the United States. Only a small number of letters have survived. One early letter offers a lengthy description of her parents' activities in China. The last folder of this series contains letters by Marjorie Morse Crunden in 1941-1942 writing from Chicago to her widowed mother in Lawrencetown, Annapolis County, Nova Scotia.
    - From parents, 1925, 1929, and no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - From parents, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - From parents, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      The letters relate to her father's illness, their plans to return to Canada via London, and their arrangements for Marjorie Morse to marry Allan Crunden in London.
    - From parents, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Marjorie Morse Crunden to her mother, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Marjorie Crunden writes to her mother in Canada from Chicago where Allan Crunden is undertaking further training in obstetrics and she is taking care of their son, Robert Morse Crunden, born in 1940. Included is a photograph of Robert.
  - Letters from Allan Bernard Crunden, Jr. to Marjorie Morse, 1935-1940; 2
    This subseries contains hundreds of letters written by Allan B. Crunden, Jr. to Marjorie Morse from before their formal engagement in 1935 to periods when were married but living apart in 1938 and 1940. Marjorie Morse met Allan Crunden, of Montclair, New Jersey, in New Haven where he was a Yale medical student (Class of 1937) and she was a student at the Yale School of Nursing. At the end of 1935, Crunden decided not to continue his medical education at Yale and instead enrolled in the fall of 1936 at Temple University School of Medicine for his clinical years. He graduated in 1938. Marjorie Morse graduated from Yale School of Nursing in 1937. They married in July 1937. The next batch of correspondence takes place in the summer of 1938 when Allan Crunden was taking courses at Columbia and Marjorie Crunden was visiting her parents in Canada and then serving for six weeks as a nurse for the summer program of the Institute of Euthenics at Vassar College. For the last batch of letters in 1940, Allan Crunden was doing a residency in Jersey City, New Jersey and Marjorie Crunden was living in Montclair and studying for a master's degree in education at Teacher's College, Columbia University.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Marjorie Morse met Allan Crunden in the fall of 1934 and by the early spring of 1935, she had visited his parents in Montclair. He was trying to persuade her to become engaged to him. See Box 2, folder 13. In these letters, Allan notes that he is corresponding with Marjorie's father in China, sending him medical books and journal issues. (He continues to do this throughout the courtship.) In the summer Allan writes from his parents' home in Montclair to Marjorie in Lawrencetown, Annapolis County, Nova Scotia (henceforth Lawrencetown), where her father's family lived. Later letters are to Marjorie in New Haven. One letter, 1935 October 21, suggests various disagreements. An important letter of 1935 December 10 discusses why he wants to complete his medical studies elsewhere than at Yale where he is currently enrolled. See also undated letters, Box 2, Folder 12.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 January-February (Box 1, Folder 7)
      These letters are from Allan in Montclair to Marjorie in New Haven and then to her at Butler Hospital, Providence, Rhode Island, where she is doing a psychiatric nursing rotation. He is taking courses at Columbia University on clinical diagnosis and sex education for children. Sometime before February 1936, Allan's mother had died. He and his father are settling the estate.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 March 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Letters are to Marjorie at Butler Hospital, Providence, Rhode Island. He mentions taking his father to hear talks at New York Academy of Medicine by Yale professors including Ashley Oughterson and Clements C. Fry. He has gotten permission from the registrar to take some courses in May at the Post-Graduate Medical School attached to Columbia University.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 March 16-20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Letters are written to Marjorie Morse at Charles V. Chapin Hospital, Providence, Rhode Island, where she is doing a clinical rotation. Marjorie has had scarlet fever and there is further discusssion of a scarlet fever epidemic.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Letters written to Marjorie Morse at Charles V. Chapin Hospital.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Marjorie Morse has returned to her usual address, the Yale School of Nursing dormitory at 350 Congress Avenue. By May 18 she is living in the nurses dormitory at William Wirt Winchester Hospital, West Haven, the tuberculosis sanitarium of New Haven Hospital, where she is on rotation. The letters discuss politics of the 1936 election. Allan and his father are staunch Republicans opposed to Franklin Roosevelt and the New Deal. Allan sends Marjorie a telegram on May 27 with his medical board examination scores.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Letters are to Marjorie Morse at William Wirt Winchester Hospital, and then at 350 Congress Ave., New Haven. Allan's letter of June 2 describes his visit to Temple University, Philadelphia, and the improbable story of how he got admitted as a third year student to the Medical School. He sends a clipping on tennis tournaments in the Montclair area. Marjorie is an expert tennis player. The letter of June 13 mentions politics.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 July (Box 1, Folder 13)
      For part of the month, Marjorie is visiting relatives in Nova Scotia. Allan begins a trip out West with his father.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 August (Box 1, Folder 14)
      For most of the month, Allan writes from National Parks in western United States and in Canada where he is traveling with his father.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 September (Box 1, Folder 15)
      The September 9 letter includes four photographs of Allan Crunden and Marjorie Morse. Later in September, Allan Crunden moves to Philadelphia where he is living in the Psi Chi Medical Fraternity dormitory. He starts his clinical training at Temple University School of Medicine.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 October 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      In this and later months, Allan writes about working on the wards and the frequent examinations he has to take. He is much interested in their eventual marriage and sends news and clippings related to weddings.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 October 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 November (Box 1, Folder 18)
      He writes about the election and about Mrs. Roosevelt's post-election visit to Temple University. He comments on a clipping, "She appears to be unmuzzled again."
    - From Allan Crunden, 1936 December (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - From Allan Crunden, 1937 January 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      In his January 2 letter, he mentions his negative view of women doctors, and the issue of their differing religions. See also Box 2, Folder 12 on this issue. He continues to write about various clinics and examinations.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1937 January 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      He writes in some detail about clinical training in obstetrics, his eventual specialty.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1937 February (Box 1, Folder 22)
      On February 23, he sends a clipping of Dr. Tyson's pediatrics examination.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1937 March (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - From Allan Crunden, 1937 April 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      In his letter of April 7, he asks if she has the nerve to get Harvey Cushing to autograph his copy of Consecratio Medici. He will be going on the wards on April 15.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1937 April 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      He is on the ward and in private homes doing obstetrics. He writes about having wedding invitations made, although the date and place of the wedding is still undecided, and depends on whether and when Marjorie's parents can get to the wedding. He wants to be married as soon as possible. His father is remarrying in August.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1937 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
      On May 9, he notes that he's been asked to edit his medical class's yearbook. On May 24, he writes on the other side of professor Babcock's "Final Examination in Surgery." The wedding place and date remain undecided.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1937 June (Box 2, Folder 4)
      They will be sailing to London for their wedding but the actual date is undecided, because it is not clear when her parents will arrive from China. They may need to have a legal waiting period before they can get married. If the wedding is delayed too long, they will travel in England on their own, since they have to get back to the U.S. by August.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1938 June 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Having graduated from Yale School of Nursing in May 1937, Marjorie Morse married Allan Crunden in London on July 10, 1937 and spent the school year 1937-1938 in Philadelphia. He completed his medical degree while she worked as a nurse-administrator at the Temple University School of Nursing. The letters from Allan Crunden to Marjorie Morse Crunden resume in June 1938 when she is visiting her parents in Lawrencetown. He sends her his grades and the "Final Examination in Senior Surgery" with Prof. Babcock. She has been invited to serve as nurse at the six-week summer program for children of the Vassar College, Summer Institute of Euthenics. Euthenics, the name of a Vassar department, meant right living and was a positive form of eugenics. On June 2, he mentioned that he was officer of the day at a base hospital.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1938 June 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      He has been assigned to a base hospital at Fort George Meade in Maryland. She has returned from Lawrencetown and is in Montclair.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1938 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
      He has gotten a room in New York and is taking courses in social psychology at Columbia University. She is at the Vassar College Summer Institute of Euthenics serving as a nurse. He notes on July 14 that Columbia seems to be a "perpetual hotbed of dissention."
    - From Allan Crunden, 1938 August (Box 2, Folder 8)
      He writes more about his courses at Columbia. They plan to travel out West after she returns from Vassar.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1940 July 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Letters from Allan Crunden in Jersey City, N.J., where he is doing residency work at the Margaret Hague Maternity Hospital, to Marjorie Crunden in Lawrencetown. He describes his work at the hospital. His letter postmarked July 2 mentions seeing a review of Marjorie Crunden's book in American Journal of Nursing. She had written a pamphlet, Selected Readings and References for the Teacher of Sociology for Nurses, published by the National League of Nursing Education in 1940.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1940 July 16-31 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      He writes more about his residency and encloses anti-Roosevelt clippings.
    - From Allan Crunden, 1940 August (Box 2, Folder 11)
      He has accepted an invitation to take part of his residency at Doctors Hospital, New York, and writes to her from there.
    - From Allan Crunden, no date (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Folder contains two letters and two cards enclosed with gifts of flowers. One letter is about their religious differences and is from an early date.
  - Letters from Marjorie Morse to members of the "Which Club" (friends from Wellesley), 1934-1937; 3
    The "Which Club" or the "Whichers" were friends from Wellesley College who sent out a round robin set of letters. When the robin returned to a member, she substituted a new letter, and sent the set on to the next person. Thus Marjorie Morse's letters were returned to her. Her letters discuss her nursing school education, her relationship with Allan Crunden, and the work and relationships of her friends. Among the friends mentioned are Peg Burchard, Mary Lou Henry, Grace (Gigi) Hoyer, "Psyche," and Sylvia ("Silly").
    - Marjorie Morse to the Which Club, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Marjorie Morse to the Which Club, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters from friends and family to Marjorie Morse (Crunden), 1927-1938; 4
    - From friends and family, 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Letters from friends in school, Chip, Lewis, and Alice, and from older friends and relatives, Eleanor A. Griffith (Montreal), Aunt Pearl (Lawrencetown), and "Mother West" (Springfield, Mass.)
    - From friends and family, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Invitation to a dance from Bill Dickenson, and telegraph from Delta Delta Delta.
    - From friends and family, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Letters from Marvin Bendiner, The Aardvark, and Ralph at Dartmouth College. See also Box 3, Folder 8 for possible related material.
    - From friends and family, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Letters from Jane B. Dye, Chengtu, China, Pete (Medford, Mass.), a card from England from Churchill(?), and a Christmas card from Sidney P. Wheelock (Oxford University). Yale student Bill Gordon(?) sends a letter about the National Student League at Yale and his picketing at the New Haven foundry strike. He writes of allegations made against "May Morse." See also Box 3, Folder 8 for other letters that may be from this period.
    - From friends and family, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Letters from Aunt Gertrude (Mrs. Fred T. Field of Newton, Mass.), Aunt Floyd (Mrs. A. H. C. Floyd of Melrose, Mass.), Andy, Peg, Sarah B. Downer, and Ivy Carr. An interesting long letter from Dr. Max Taffel at Yale describes the circumstances in which he played in a tennis double against Marjorie Morse.
    - From Su-Yuin Wang and related materials, 1935 November - 1936 February (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Su-Yuin Wang was a Chinese student studying in the Kyoto Girl's College in Japan who sent a letter and a greeting card to Yale, seeking a penpal to write to her. The folder also contains a letter to Marjorie Morse from Yale President, James A. Angell, sending the letter and the card; and a note to Miss Effie Taylor, Dean of the Yale School of Nursing, saying that Marjorie Morse left the correspondence for her to see. Su-Yuin Wang replies that her brother, Ying-Hua Wang, at Kalee University, will be coming to the United States and she hopes Marjorie will meet him. She encloses his photograph. See also Box 2, Folders 24 and 25.
    - From friends and family, 1936 March (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Letter from Alfred H. Morse, Morse Sand & Gravel Co., Pawtucket, R.I.
    - From friends and family, 1936 June (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Letter from Frank and Mary (Lawrencetown), and telegram from Bill Tilden.
    - From friends and family, 1936 July (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Letters from Uncle Charlie and Aunt (Mrs. S.A.) Floyd.
    - From friends and family, 1936 August-September (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Letters from Theodore H. Gregg who is interested in writing to a Chinese student studying in Japan, Uncle Charlie, Aunt Nell (Yarmouth, N.S., who is concerned about Morse's family's possible reaction that her fiancé is Catholic), Ruth Worten (friend from Newton High School now working at Harvard Medical School), and John W. Hickey (on tennis). See Box 2, Folders 20 and 25 on the Chinese student, Su-Yuin Wang.
    - From friends and family, 1936 October (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Letters from Aunt Gertrude, Jennette Foster(?), Edward H. Hume, M.D., John W. Hickey, Gigi (Grace Hoyer), cousin Frank W. Morse, and a lengthy letter from Su-Yuin Wang (Peiping, China). See Box 2, Folder 20.
    - From friends and family, 1936 December (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Letters from John W. Hickey, Ann (a child?), Aunt Pearl (Lawrencetown), Angel(?), Uncle George, and Aunt Floyd.
    - From friends and family, 1937 January-March (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Letters from Frank Morse (Lawrencetown), Allan B. Crunden, Sr. (on her father's illness), Uncle Charlie, John W. Hickey (tennis), Mrs. Peakes(?), Aunt Floyd, Aunt Gertrude (on the importance of timing the wedding so that Marjorie Morse's parents can attend), Alice Carlin (fiancée of Alan B. Crunden, Sr.), and Aunt Peral and Aunt Ella. Many of these letters are about her parents leaving China and arrangements for the wedding.
    - From friends and family, 1937 April-May (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Letters from "Pish," Aunt Ella, Aunt Charlotte Swan (Providence, R. I.), "Silly" (Sylvia), Gigi (Grace Hoyer), May Cascallen (Whitby, Ontario), and E. W. Fisher (Pleasantville, N.Y.), and Uncle Charlie. Much of the correspondence concerns Morse's parents and the wedding in London.
    - From friends and family, 1937 June (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Letters from Aunt Pearl, Psyche, Uncle George, Aunt Nell, Sylvia, Grace Hoyer (her fiancé called the wedding off), Murray and Sally, and Mrs. Leonard J. Saccio. On June 18, Psyche writes to Marjorie Morse who is aboard the Steamer Lafayette.
    - From friends and family, 1937 July (Box 3, Folder 4)